# Clayton H. Sanford

claytonsanford.com  $\diamond$  clayton@cs.columbia.edu  $\diamond$  (831) 332-0431 LinkedIn: in/claytonsanford  $\diamond$  Github: chsanford

### EXECUTIVE SUMMARY

Machine learning researcher and theoretical computer scientist with NSF GRFP support and a publication record at top-tier ML venues (NeurIPS, COLT) on the fundamental representational and generalization properties of feed-forward neural networks, recurrent neural networks, and transformers.

Creative and adaptable interdisciplinary researcher with published empirical work on the intersections of machine learning/data science and climate modeling, dynamical systems, and molecular biology.

Skilled data scientist and engineer with successful internships at Google Research, Microsoft Research, and Allen Institute for AI (Outstanding Intern award) and full-time employment at LinkedIn.

Effective communicator and leader in technical research, teaching, academic service, and local government.

### CORE COMPETENCIES

Machine Learning & Artificial Intelligence ⋄ Python and Java ⋄ Deep Learning in Pytorch Mathematical Modeling ⋄ Data Analytics (Hadoop, Spark, SQL) ⋄ Dynamical Systems and Climate Modeling Communication and Leadership ⋄ Technical and Academic Writing ⋄ Public Speaking

#### **EDUCATION**

Columbia University

September 2019 — May 2024

Ph.D. in Computer Science

New York, NY

· Advisors: Daniel Hsu and Rocco Servedio.

**Brown University** 

September 2014 — May 2018

Sc.B. with Honors in Applied Math - Computer Science, Magna Cum Laude

Providence, RI

#### EXPERIENCE

Research Scientist Google Research August 2024 — present

New York, NY

Student Researcher

Google Research

January 2024 — May 2024

New York, NY

· Runs experiments and proves theorems about transformers' fundamental limitations and graph algorithm capabilities.

# **Applied Sciences Intern**

Microsoft Research

May 2023 — August 2023

New York, NY

- · Trained transformer models with up to 500 million parameters to learn combinatorial search tasks with behavioral cloning and chain-of-thought reasoning.
- · Proved theoretical results about the advantages of transformers over graph neural networks (GNNs) for identifying isomorphisms between different combinatorial problems, to support empirical results. (Manuscript in progress.)

### Research Intern (PhD)

Allen Institute for AI

May 2022 — August 2022

Seattle, WA

- · Improved reliability and quality of annual temperature and humidity estimates of ML-corrected coarse-grid climate model with novelty detection.
- · Presentations at NeurIPS 2022 climate ML workshop and American Meteorological Society.
- · Contributions recognized with Outstanding Intern award.

## Associate Data Scientist

LinkedIn

August 2018 — April 2019 San Francisco, CA

· Analyzed usage patterns of LinkedIn Learning, conducted A/B tests, and tracked metrics with Hive and Spark.

### **PUBLICATIONS**

### Neural networks

- · C. Sanford, B. Fatemi, E. Hall, A. Tsitsulin, M. Kazemi, J. Halcrow, B. Perozzi, V. Mirrokni. "Understanding Transformer Reasoning Capabilities via Graph Algorithms." *Preprint*.
- · C. Sanford, D. Hsu, M. Telgarsky. "Transformers perform parallel computation in log-depth." ICML 2024.
- · C. Sanford, D. Hsu, M. Telgarsky. "Representational strengths and limitations of transformers." NeurIPS 2023.
- · N. Ardeshir\*, D Hsu\*, C. Sanford\*. "Intrinsic dimensionality and generalization properties of the R-norm inductive bias." COLT 2023.
- · A. Bietta\*, J. Bruna\*, C. Sanford\*, M. Song\*. "Learning single-index models with shallow neural networks." NeurIPS 2022.
- · V. Chatziafratis\*, I. Panageas\*, C. Sanford\*, S. Stavroulakis\*. "On scrambling phenomena for randomly initialized recurrent networks." NeurIPS 2022.
- · D. Hsu\*, C. Sanford\*, R. Servedio\*, E.-V. Vlatakis-Gkaragkounis\*. "Near-Optimal Statistical Query Lower Bounds for Agnostically Learning Intersections of Halfspaces with Gaussian Marginals." COLT 2022.
- · C. Sanford, V. Chatziafratis. "Expressivity of Neural Networks via Chaotic Itineraries beyond Sharkovsky's Theorem." AISTATS 2022.
- · N. Ardeshir\*, C. Sanford\*, D. Hsu. "Support vector machines and linear regression coincide with very high-dimensional features." NeurIPS 2021.
- · D. Hsu\*, C. Sanford\*, R. Servedio\*, E.-V. Vlatakis-Gkaragkounis\*. "On the Approximation Power of Two-Layer Networks of Random ReLUs." *COLT 2021*.

### Interdisciplinary ML and data science

- · C. Sanford, A. Kwa, O. Watt-Meyer, S. Clark, N. Brenowitz, J. McGibbon, C. Bretherton. "Improving the predictions of ML-corrected climate models with novelty detection." Appearing in Journal of Advances in Modeling Earth Systems.
- · T. Chin\*, J. Ruth\*, C. Sanford\*, R. Santorella\*, P. Carter, B. Sandstede. "Enabling equation-free modeling via diffusion maps." *Journal of Dynamics and Differential Equations*, 2022.
- · K. Cygan\*, C. Sanford\*, W. Fairbrother. "Spliceman2 A Computational Web Server That Predicts Sequence Variations in Pre-mRNA Splicing." *Bioinformatics* 33 (18), 2017.

### **AWARDS**

NSF GRFP Fellow March 2021

# Outstanding Intern Award, Allen Institute for AI

December 2022

Awarded to four summer interns who went above and beyond as researchers and as colleagues (cash prize).

### Paul Charles Michelman Memorial Award

May 2023

Given to a PhD student in Computer Science who has performed exemplary service to the department, devoting time and effort beyond the call to further the department's goals (cash prize).

### Department Service Award, Columbia Computer Science

May 2020, 2022, 2023

### Senior Prize, Brown Computer Science

May 2018

Awarded to the top students in the Computer Science department by faculty selection (cash prize).

# Outstanding Winner, Interdisciplinary Contest in Modeling

April 2016

Top 5 teams out of over 3000 in 96-hour math modeling competition on water scarcity.

### TEACHING AND SERVICE

 $\textbf{Reviewer:} \ \ \text{AAAI 2024, FOCS 2024, ICLR 2024, ALT 2024, NeurIPS 2023, JMLR 2023, SODA 2022, STOC 2022.}$ 

### Teaching Assistant, Brown and Columbia Universities

September 2015 — December 2023

### PhD Representative, Columbia Computer Science

September 2022 — May 2024

Serves as liaison between computer science students, faculty, and administrators and attends faculty meetings.

### Community Board Member, Manhattan Community Board 9

May 2023 — present

Appointed by the borough president to represent community needs of a district on the west side of Manhattan between 110th and 155th St. Serves on Economic Development and LGBTQ Committees.

### President, qSTEM

September 2022 — September 2023

Led a team of student organizers in planning events for LGBTQ+ students at the Columbia School of Engineering.